<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>emacs on Vedang Manerikar</title>
    <link>https://vedang.me/tags/emacs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in emacs on Vedang Manerikar</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 23:18:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://vedang.me/tags/emacs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to use the Clojure REBL with Leiningen, Cider and Emacs</title>
      <link>https://vedang.me/blog/clj-rebl-lein-cider-emacs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 23:18:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vedang.me/blog/clj-rebl-lein-cider-emacs/</guid>
      <description>Note: This set of instructions only work on Clojure 1.10+, Lein 2.9+ and JDK 11+. Also, REBL requires a license for commercial use.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t find a handy reference to getting started with REBL if your primary workflow is Leiningen/nrepl, so here is the series of things I had to do to get the REBL up and running for myself.
  Download the REBL jar from Cognitect.
  Use lein-localrepo to install the REBL jar to your m2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compiling and Running Emacs 28 from the native-comp feature branch (Ubuntu 20.04).</title>
      <link>https://vedang.me/tinylog/emacs-28-native-comp-ubuntu-20-04/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2020 12:35:23 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vedang.me/tinylog/emacs-28-native-comp-ubuntu-20-04/</guid>
      <description>Quick Note: How to compile Emacs 28.0.5 from source with native compilation: https://t.co/29vNNkGQoU
Native Comp is the work of Andrea Corallo, compiling emacslisp to native code and making it blazing fast! https://t.co/A9oR5mJC9G
&amp;mdash; Vedang Manerikar (@vedang) August 23, 2020  The gist of it, building Emacs from Source git clone https://git.savannah.gnu.org/git/emacs.git cd emacs ./autogen.sh ./configure --with-nativecomp # If everything works make # Test the binary src/emacs -Q # Install the binary sudo make install # If you want to re-build from scratch make distclean Problems during Installation Configure fails because libgccjit fails the smoketest   Ensure that libgccjit is installed and at the latest version (at this point in time, the latest version is 10)</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>