<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tiny snippets of useful information. on Vedang Manerikar</title>
    <link>https://vedang.me/tinylog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tiny snippets of useful information. on Vedang Manerikar</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2020 17:56:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://vedang.me/tinylog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Compiling and Running Emacs 28 from the native-comp feature branch (Ubuntu 20.04).</title>
      <link>https://vedang.me/tinylog/emacs-28-native-comp-ubuntu-20-04/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2020 12:35:23 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vedang.me/tinylog/emacs-28-native-comp-ubuntu-20-04/</guid>
      <description>Quick Note: How to compile Emacs 28.0.5 from source with native compilation: https://t.co/29vNNkGQoU
Native Comp is the work of Andrea Corallo, compiling emacslisp to native code and making it blazing fast! https://t.co/A9oR5mJC9G
&amp;mdash; Vedang Manerikar (@vedang) August 23, 2020  The gist of it, building Emacs from Source git clone https://git.savannah.gnu.org/git/emacs.git cd emacs ./autogen.sh ./configure --with-nativecomp # If everything works make # Test the binary src/emacs -Q # Install the binary sudo make install # If you want to re-build from scratch make distclean Problems during Installation Configure fails because libgccjit fails the smoketest   Ensure that libgccjit is installed and at the latest version (at this point in time, the latest version is 10)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Programmer&#39;s Guide to Wisdom</title>
      <link>https://vedang.me/tinylog/programmer-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2020 17:15:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vedang.me/tinylog/programmer-guide/</guid>
      <description>This poster captures timeless advice on programming, I keep a copy on my desk to read whenever I can.
Over the weekend, I created a poster for my desk. It captures timeless best practices and advice on programming and software design. Presenting it here, in the hopes that it&amp;#39;ll be useful to others as well. Features: @esrtweet, Doug McIlroy, @rob_pike and @RealGeneKim pic.twitter.com/Lj2kUqwq2J
&amp;mdash; Vedang Manerikar (@vedang) August 10, 2020  I collect such deeply useful and universal advice under the tag wisdom, if you want to read more posts of this kind.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tinylog: Mbsync: Error: Channel &lt;x&gt; Is Locked</title>
      <link>https://vedang.me/tinylog/mbsync-channel-is-locked/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2017 19:22:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vedang.me/tinylog/mbsync-channel-is-locked/</guid>
      <description>You may come across the following error when running mbsync :
Error: channel :&amp;lt;channel-name&amp;gt;-remote:&amp;lt;folder&amp;gt;-:&amp;lt;channel-name&amp;gt;-local:&amp;lt;folder&amp;gt; is locked This happens when there is another mbsync instance running in parallel and it has taken a lock on the particular folder. In my case, I am running mbsync via a cron-job, and it tends to leave dead instances around if the laptop sleeps during a run. Kill all instances of mbsync and restart the process and you should be fine!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>