<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Clojure on Vedang Manerikar</title>
    <link>https://vedang.me/categories/clojure/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Clojure on Vedang Manerikar</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://vedang.me/categories/clojure/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Lazy Weekend Reading: A love letter to Clojure</title>
      <link>https://vedang.me/techlog/lazy-weekend-reading-love-letter-to-clojure/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vedang.me/techlog/lazy-weekend-reading-love-letter-to-clojure/</guid>
      <description>I had no idea that Gene Kim, author of three books that have garnered wide-spread public acclaim, was doing Clojure programming. (They are DevOps Handbook, Phoenix Project, and Accelerate &amp;ndash; we&amp;rsquo;ve ordered them recently for the Helpshift Library). He published a love-letter to Clojure this weekend, and I think it is an absolute must-read for all programmers (whether you write Clojure or not). The blog-post covers the following areas:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simulating the Passport Seva Kendra using Clojure</title>
      <link>https://vedang.me/techlog/2018-12-15-simulating-the-passport-seva-kendra/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vedang.me/techlog/2018-12-15-simulating-the-passport-seva-kendra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cross-posted from my post on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/helpshift-engineering/simulating-the-passport-seva-kendra-using-clojure-fd88c12dde8c&#34;&gt;Helpshift Engineering Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year ago, I went to the Passport Seva Kendra (PSK) in Mundhwa, Pune
to get my passport renewed. At the time, the government had revamped
this process and made it a simple, step-in/step-out painless affair.
Unfortunately for me, I hit an edge-case in the system and took much
longer than expected to complete. I was there for close to 4 hours. I
used this time to observe the behavior of the PSK and think about
ways to improve the applicant experience. I thought it was an
interesting problem to solve and write about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, my wife booked an appointment at the PSK to renew &lt;span class=&#34;underline&#34;&gt;her&lt;/span&gt;
passport and this provided the spark I needed to write about it. So
here we are, a year later, talking about the passport renewal process
at the PSK.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>